Guide to the Kurt Stone Papers
Yale University Music Library
Kurt Stone papers
1930-1986
MSS 71
Yale University Music Library
4.75
(6 boxes)
The Kurt Stone Papers highlight Stone's interest in contemporary music. His work on twentieth-century musical notation is well documented, including notes, lectures and published articles. The collection contains substantial professional and personal correspondence with Elliott Carter and Paul Hindemith. A significant portion of the Carter correspondence details the publication of Carter's Double Concerto. Also notable is a full score of the fourth movement of Charles Ives' Fourth Symphony, with annotations by Stone.
Stone, Kurt
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Else Stone, 1988 and 1992.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated material: The Kurt Stone Collection, at the University of North Carolina Wilmington Special Collections and Archives.
Separated Materials
Manuscript score by Heitor Villa-Lobos, String Quartet no. 7 (1942), removed from collection and added to Music Library holdings as Misc. Ms. 616.
Biographical / Historical
Kurt Stone (previously known as Kurt Salomon) was born in Hamburg, Germany in 1911. He studied piano privately with Walter Kraft from 1931 to 1933, and began a music degree at Hamburg University. In 1933, Stone fled Germany. He relocated to Copenhagen, and began his studies at The Royal Danish Music Conservatory. In Copenhagen, Stone met his wife Else, who had also fled Nazi Germany. Stone graduated in 1937, specializing in piano, harpsichord and music theory, but was unable to obtain a work visa in Denmark. Stone decided to relocate to the U.S., while Else remained in Denmark. She was later evacuated to Sweden, when Germany invaded Denmark.
In 1938, Stone came to New York on the affidavit of a cousin. He taught piano and musicianship privately, and was hired by the Dalcroze School of Music. During his six years at Dalcroze, Stone entered the field of music publishing as a freelance editor (under Arthur Mendel, among others). After a one-year position at the music reference division of The New York Public Library, Stone was hired as the editorial head of the orchestra and band department at G. Schirmer, Inc., in 1950.
In 1956, Stone was appointed editor-in-chief of Associated Music Publishers, Inc. After the firm's sale to G. Schirmer, he left for Alexander Broude, Inc., where he became director of publication from 1965 to 1969. From 1969 to 1976, Stone was director of publication at Joseph Boonin, Inc.
As an editor, Stone worked mostly with contemporary twentieth-century composers, such as Milton Babbit, Earle Brown, Elliott Carter, Henry Cowell, Paul Hindemith, Charles Ives, Arnold Schoenberg and Virgil Thomson. Stone also produced his own editions of 14th-19th century music, including the works of J.C. Bach, Buxtehude, Gesualdo, and Schütz. Stone produced copious liner notes for recordings, as well as articles and reviews.
Stone became increasingly aware of musical miscommunication between contemporary composers and the performers of their music. This interest led to Stone's establishment of the Index of New Musical Notation at the New York Public Library at Lincoln Center in 1971. This project, funded by the Ford and Rockefeller Foundations, culminated in an international conference on new music notation in Belgium, in 1974. A Guggenheim Fellowship supported Stone's publication of his textbook, Music Notation in the Twentieth Century: A Practical Guidebook (W.W. Norton, 1980). Another notable publication, The Writings of Elliott Carter (Indiana University Press, 1977), was compiled, edited and annotated by Stone and his wife, Else, who were good friends of Elliott Carter and his wife, Helen.
Kurt Stone died in June of 1989, in Wilmington, North Carolina.
Scope and Contents
The Kurt Stone Papers highlight Stone's interest in contemporary music. His work on twentieth-century musical notation is well documented, including notes, lectures and published articles. The collection contains substantial professional and personal correspondence with Elliott Carter and Paul Hindemith. A significant portion of the Carter correspondence details the publication of Carter's Double Concerto. Also notable is a full score of Charles Ives' Fourth Symphony with annotations by Stone.
While there is a wealth of correspondence with Carter and Hindemith, the collection does not contain correspondence with other contemporary composers with whom Stone worked. While the collection contains notable examples of edited scores, chiefly Ives' Fourth Symphony, there is not enough musical material to fully document Stone's editorial process.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Personal and professional papers, 1931-1988. II. Elliott Carter, 1939-1986. III. Paul Hindemith, 1945-1973.
Musical notation -- 20th Century; Stone, Kurt; Hindemith, Paul, 1895-1963; Carter, Elliott, 1908-2012
- Personal and professional papers, 1931-1988; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is comprised of material spanning from 1937 to 1988. It includes correspondence and documents related to Stone's graduation from the Royal Danish Music Conservatory in 1937, his subsequent move to New York in 1938, and his career in music publishing from the 1950s through the 1980s. Stone's writings and lectures on twentieth-century notation are included, as well as manuscript music.
  Correspondence with and regarding Elliott Carter and Paul Hindemith is contained in Series II and Series III, respectively.
  - Biographical material, 1938-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    The material includes biographical sketches, resumes, and memorabilia.
  - Correspondence, 1931-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
    Some letters are in German and Danish.
  - Writing and lectures
    - General writings and notes, Circa 1940-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      General
      Includes editorial notes, and text written by "Kurtrude Stone" in the style of Gertrude Stein.
    - Published writings and lectures, 1936-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Program and liner notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes drafts and edits by Stone and others.
      - Liner notes (oversize), 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Research notes and edits for Music Notation in the Twentieth Century: A Practical Guidebook, Circa 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Reviews of Stone's publications, 1950-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Publications by others, Circa 1950-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - James Thurber drawing, Circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    The drawing may be original.
  - Materials related to Ives 4th Symphony premiere, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript music, Circa 1950-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript music by others
    - Charles Ives 4th Symphony score, fourth movement, Circa 1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Manuscript score transcribed by Theodore A. Seder and annotated by Stone, indicating differences between score and parts.
    - "For Kurt: Some very mild enigma variations in celebration of the crushing 50th birthday", 1961 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Published music by Halsey Stevens, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Elliott Carter, 1939-1986; Series II
  Series II is chiefly comprised of correspondence between Stone and Carter, from 1954 to 1981. In their letters, Carter and Stone discuss the viability of publishing Carter's various compositions, the performance and reception of Carter's pieces, and contractual issues with Associated Music Publishers. Also included is correspondence related to Carter, and correspondence between Carter and others. The series also contains reviews (1953-1986) and programs (1939-1986).
  - Correspondence
    - Stone and Carter, 1954-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
    - Stone regarding Carter, 1953-1962
      - 1953-1962 (Box 3, Folder 8-12)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Carter and others, 1954-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Reviews and programs
    - Reviews, 1953-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Programs, 1939-1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Oversize programs, 1963-1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Program notes, 1956-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript music, 1947-1961 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    This folder contains pages 68-69 of a ballet, possibly Minotaur, and a Plan of Introduction for the Double Concerto.
- Paul Hindemith, 1945-1973; Series III
  Series III contains correspondence, programs, and publicity related to Paul Hindemith. The majority of correspondence consists of Stone's letters to Hindemith; only one, undated letter from Hindemith is included. Much of the correspondence concerns Paul Hindemith: Catalogue of Published Works and Recordings, which was prepared by Stone and published in 1954. Several drafts and proofs of the catalogue can be found in this series. Stone corresponded with Hindemith until his death in 1963. Several obituaries and memorial concert programs are included in this series.
  - Correspondence
    - Stone to Hindemith, 1945-1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Some letters are in German.
    - Stone regarding Hindemith, 1953-1973 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Writings, 1959, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Consists of notes for "Six Madrigals" and annotated lyrics for "Ten Madrigals".
  - Programs and publicity, 1958-1971
    - Programs, 1958-1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Publicity, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Liner notes, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Liner notes for "Hindemith: Der Schwanendreher & Herodiade" Vox Productions (1952).
  - Catalogues and obituaries, Circa 1950-1963
    - Paul Hindemith: Catalogue of Published Works and Recordings (drafts and proofs), Circa 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Obituaries and photographs, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 9)